Matthew Smith - Software Developer

msmith1392@gmail.com

https://msmith1392.github.io/

Core Expertise: Java (Spring Boot, Maven, Gradle), Python (Django), JavaScript/TypeScript (React, Angular, Svelte, Node.js, NPM), Relational Databases (MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server), Git

Federal + Private Sector Experience

Based in KY | Open to Remote Roles in the USA. | Open to Roles in KY.

Summary

Skilled Software Developer with over 10 years of experience in full-stack development, primarily in Java-based environments. Strong background working on federal contracts (FEMA PrepToolkit) with an emphasis on maintainable, secure, and scalable systems. Proven success in both legacy and modern stacks including Spring Boot, Django, GWT, React, Angular, and Svelte. Over 6 years of experience working remotely. Self-driven, communicative, and delivery focused.

Professional Experience

Software Engineer | 4 Arrows Consulting (FEMA Contract - PrepToolkit) • 2019-Present

- Contributed to multiple modules of FEMA's PrepToolkit, including the Unified Reporting
 Tool (URT), Radiological Emergency Preparedness Program (REPP) Exercises, and supporting
 local, regional, federal, and private sector partners with Homeland Security Exercise and
 Evaluation Program (HSEEP) Exercises.
- Led enhancements and updates to URT assessment systems for each fiscal year cycle.
- Supported the migration of legacy components from max.gov to PrepToolkit. These
 components are Threat and Hazard Identification and Risk Assessment (THIRA),
 Comprehensive Preparedness Guide (CPG), National Incident Management System (NIMS),
 and Urban Area Working Group (UAWG)
- Participated in architecture discussions, code reviews, and estimation for both GWT-based and serverless/Svelte modules.
- Supported containerized Java microservices built with Quarkus, deployed using Podman.
- Maintained high code quality using version control, CM tools, and test-driven practices.
- Mentored junior developers, providing guidance on code quality, troubleshooting, and best practices across both legacy and modern stacks, as well as assisting with their understanding of architectural patterns across project modules.

Tech Stack: Java, Spring Boot, Gradle, Quarkus, Google Web Toolkit (GWT), MySQL, Liferay 7, Apache HTTP Server, JavaScript/TypeScript, Svelte, Node.js, NPM, AWS Lambda, Git

Applications Developer | United Parcel Service (UPS) • Louisville, KY • 2017–2019

- Maintained and enhanced enterprise logistics systems used across UPS ground operations.
- Developed UI features for a real-time transportation visibility system.
- Collaborated across teams to implement and test new features from requirements through deployment.
- Translated requirements into discrete rules for the Drools inference engine to process.
- Conducted system performance testing using Apache JMeter and HP Roadrunner.
- Delivered features on a three-week agile sprint cycle.
- Provided 24/7 production support (on rotation with the rest of the team members).

Tech Stack: Java, Spring Framework, Maven/Gradle Drools (BRMS), WebLogic, ActiveMQ, SQL Server, TFVC

Software Developer | Apax Software • Lexington, KY • 2016–2017

- Managed multiple projects and client requests simultaneously, using GitHub Flow for deployment and version control.
- Developed web applications for clients including Presbyterian Church (USA) and University
 of Kentucky's College of Public Health.
- Built custom CMS tools, event registration systems, nomination management, and online surveys for Presbyterian Church (USA) using Python/Django and AngularJS.
- Heavily involved in the full software development lifecycle of a project for University of Kentucky's College of Public Health, including a mobile web app (Fit Face-Off), and interactive wellness tool for team and individual fitness challenges.

Tech Stack: Python, Django, JavaScript (AngularJS, jQuery), Bootstrap, AWS, Git, PHP, Drupal

Programming Analyst | Knowledge Facilitations Group (KFG) • Richmond, KY • 2015–2016

- Worked with teammates on KFG's Electronic Data Interchange (EDI) platform, EDITRACE.
- Developed backend Python components for EDITRACE's translation, validation, and mapping engine, collaborating closely with the Business Analyst.
- Built tools to process and validate data in a variety of formats, including XML, X12, EDIFACT, CSV, Excel, Tradacom, JSON, and IDoc, and assisted with managing data flow to and from databases.
- Analyzed EDI processes in real-time production environments with other developers to identify and resolve transaction errors.
- Implemented a web-based console for users to inspect and analyze any aspect of the EDI process in real time.

Tech Stack: Python, EDI (X12, XML, EDIFACT, Tradacoms, JSON, IDOC), Bootstrap, Git

Education

Eastern Kentucky University – Richmond, KY B.S. in Computer Science, 2015

Technical Skills

Languages: Java, Python, JavaScript/TypeScript, SQL, Swift, Kotlin, PHP, C#, HTML, CSS **Frameworks:** Spring Boot, Quarkus, Django, GWT, React, Svelte, Angular, .NET, Bootstrap,

Tailwind

CMS & Platforms: Liferay, Drupal, AWS (Lambda, S3), Apache HTTP Server, MySQL, Postgres,

SQL Server

Dev Tools: Git, GitHub Flow, Maven, Gradle, NPM, Node.js, JMeter, ActiveMQ, WebLogic,

Docker, Podman, Kubernetes

Other: Remote Collaboration, Agile/Scrum, CI/CD Pipelines, Legacy System Modernization